<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Mentor Safety Consultants &#8211; A Safety Co Partner</title>
	<atom:link href="https://mentorsafety.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://mentorsafety.com/</link>
	<description>Your Guide to Safety</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 20:13:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/cropped-mentor-safety-icon-only2-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Mentor Safety Consultants &#8211; A Safety Co Partner</title>
	<link>https://mentorsafety.com/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>AUSTRALIA HERE I COME</title>
		<link>https://mentorsafety.com/australia-here-i-come/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Wright]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 19:03:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Mentor Safety Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[prepare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[safe environments]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mentorsafety.com/mentor-under-fire-copy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>-Carola MittagMy trip to Australia is rapidly approaching. It was booked back in January, giving me a full ten months to prepare. With each month my excitant has grown even [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/australia-here-i-come/">AUSTRALIA HERE I COME</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>-Carola Mittag</em><br>My trip to Australia is rapidly approaching. It was booked back in January, giving me a full ten months to prepare. With each month my excitant has grown even as I thought “hey, I’ve got lots of time to prepare”.</p>



<p>What does it take to prepare for a trip halfway around the world?</p>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-1 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Booking travel tickets ✓</li>



<li>Getting adequate travel and cancellation insurance ✓</li>



<li>Valid passport ✓</li>



<li>Proof of vaccination ✓</li>



<li>Arranging accommodations ✓</li>



<li>Ensuring medications are sufficient ✓</li>



<li>Electricity adaptor ✓</li>



<li>Cell phone usage internationally ✓</li>



<li>Arranging for pet care ✓</li>



<li>Arranging for house and plant care ✓</li>
</ul>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Arranging transportation to and from the airport ✓</li>



<li>Ensuring correct currency for the destination ✓</li>



<li>Planning a wardrobe for all types of weather and activities ✓</li>



<li>Mapping out itineraries so as not to waste precious time while away ✓</li>



<li>Leaving instructions in case of a catastrophic occurrence abroad ✓</li>



<li>Finally, confirming final flight and stopover times ✓</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>



<p>Some of these things are quickly achieved while others require forethought and a significant amount of time to get them right. And they can’t all be done without assistance and the help of experienced travel agents, professional advisors and, if you’re lucky, friends who have far more experience with international travel than me.</p>



<p>This is of course similar to planning for and preparing workplaces to be safe environments for workers. Much thought and organizing goes into getting it right. At a tradeshow years ago, I asked a machine shop owner/delegate what he did to prepare his workers to be safe. He told them to work safe. Period. I asked for more specific things he did for the workers; his response was the same, with the added comment “if they get hurt I’ll just hire someone new”. Now this did occur many years ago and I can only hope this owner has since retired or sold his business to a person with more foresight and sense of responsibility.</p>



<p>Each jobsite, each work assignment and each piece of equipment must be evaluated for potential risks and hazards. Risk being the possibility that something bad or unpleasant (such as injury or a loss) will happen, while a hazard is a potential source of harm or danger&nbsp;(danger is something that may cause injury or harm). And, each worker must be specifically prepared (trained) to be safe at any given jobsite, on the equipment they are being asked to use and to be told about the risks and hazards of the job they are being asked to do. This all takes massive preparation.</p>



<p>Often it is difficult for people close to a situation, or who have done the same job for a long time to objectively assess requirements or to understand legal obligations. Preparation is key and may require the assistance of an outside resource. MENTOR SAFETY wants to be that outside resource, whether to help you build your health and safety culture program and policy development from the ground up or simply to reassure you that, should a Ministry Inspector appear unexpectedly on your doorstep, you can confidently show him/her around your facility and produce all the training documents you are sure to be asked for.</p>



<p>Being prepared to the best of one’s ability is paramount. Procrastination increases the chances of something being missed or going wrong.</p>



<p>I tend to be that procrastinator; however, I now have most of the items checked off of my travel to-do list with a few weeks to spare. Let the adventure begin!</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg" alt="carola-picture" class="wp-image-7832" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-416x624.jpg 416w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-scaled.jpg 1707w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>


<p>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Watch for next month’s Blog published in the second week of November</p>



<p>Sincerely,</p>



<p>Carola Mittag</p>



<p>Consultant and Editor for Mentor Safety Consultants Inc.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/australia-here-i-come/">AUSTRALIA HERE I COME</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MENTOR SAFETY UNDER FIRE</title>
		<link>https://mentorsafety.com/mentor-under-fire/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Wright]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 12:45:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Mentor Safety Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inspection]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[personal protective equipment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[procedures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Safety Plan]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mentorsafety.com/fatal-distraction-copy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>-Carola MittagLast October I wrote about roofers. (You will have to push the ‘back’ button about eleven times at the bottom of the Blog page to take you to my [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/mentor-under-fire/">MENTOR SAFETY UNDER FIRE</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>-Carola Mittag</em><br>Last October I wrote about roofers<em>.</em> (You will have to push the ‘back’ button about eleven times at the bottom of the Blog page to take you to my Blog <em>Just Walking By.</em>)</p>



<p>Whether writing about roofers last October was a coincidence or a foreboding that something roofing-related was about to happen, I will never know.</p>



<p>On November 2<sup>nd</sup>, the training facility and home to all of Mentor’s safety training equipment came under fire, literally. I am happy to say that there were no injuries or worse; however, I want to outline the impact this event had to all parties involved.</p>



<p>Of course it is important to get to the root cause of this fire. On that day, roofers were replacing a flat-roof top using torches to heat the materials needed to create the vapour barrier. From videos I have watched, flat-roof installation is a labour-intensive process with many inherent hazards. How ever it happened, the root cause and blame needed to be determined as the facility owners and insurance companies had to reach an agreement as to who was responsible. There are so many “could have beens” that must be considered.</p>



<p>From Mentor’s health and safety standpoint, the following questions arose:</p>



<ol class="wp-block-list" type="1">
<li>Did the roofing company have a safety plan and procedures for the work to be done?</li>



<li>Were the roofers trained on correct roofing procedures, the correct use of equipment, personal protective equipment (PPE) and materials?</li>



<li>When the fire was detected, what safety protocol was in place for the roofers to follow?</li>



<li>Who was responsible for calling for help?</li>



<li>Was there a meeting place for the roofers to congregate once they descended from the roof to account for the presence of all workers?</li>
</ol>



<p>When firefighters arrived, they were able to get the fire under control, but not before significant smoke and material damage had occurred. Here are some of the things the firefighters had to consider before entering the building:</p>



<ol class="wp-block-list" type="1">
<li>Was everyone on-site accounted for?</li>



<li>What risks were present in the event that the fire couldn’t be contained and spread to neighbouring industrial units? (As it happened, an adjacent unit stored chemicals, a major and potentially hazardous situation.)</li>



<li>Did all the industrial units have their safety binders with their safety data sheets readily available?</li>



<li>Who was the spokesperson for: the roofing company, the occupants of the industrial units, anyone else with knowledge of the facility and businesses involved?</li>
</ol>



<p>After the fire was extinguished, there was much to do. While I can’t speak to the other units involved, Mentor’s post fire recovery program has been an ongoing process.</p>



<ol class="wp-block-list" type="1">
<li>The premises required inspection for structural damage and other safety concerns.</li>



<li>The various pieces of training equipment needed to be inspected for integrity and safety, e.g. the fork lift, scissor lift, personal protective equipment such as harnesses, lanyards and lifelines and the trailer used for confined space extraction training.</li>



<li>Equipment that was undamaged still needed deep cleaning to make it serviceable.</li>



<li>An alternate training facility needed to be found until the regular space is once again usable.</li>
</ol>



<p>Now, ten months later, we are hopeful to be able to occupy the restored space by early October.</p>



<p>This is a very basic summary of the actual and very alarming event that happened to our safety training company. Fortunately we can look upon it as a personal learning experience to share with all our clients. Nothing speaks louder than having lived it. If we can help others with our story, then perhaps it was worthwhile.</p>



<p>In the grand scheme of things and in deep gratitude, Mentor considers itself fortunate that this was an inconvenient but non-disastrous event. &nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg" alt="carola-picture" class="wp-image-7832" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-416x624.jpg 416w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-scaled.jpg 1707w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>


<p>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Watch for next month’s Blog published in the second week of October</p>



<p>Sincerely,</p>



<p>Carola Mittag</p>



<p>Consultant and Editor for Mentor Safety Consultants Inc.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/mentor-under-fire/">MENTOR SAFETY UNDER FIRE</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>FATAL DISTRACTION</title>
		<link>https://mentorsafety.com/fatal-distraction/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Wright]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 13:28:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Mentor Safety Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[distractions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ergonomic equipment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[policies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[training programs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mentorsafety.com/alzheimers-in-the-workplace-copy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>-Carola MittagHaving recently watched the 1987 psychological thriller Fatal Attraction, I started wondering about attractions that can actually become distractions; aren’t they really flip sides of the same coin? Examples [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/fatal-distraction/">FATAL DISTRACTION</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>-Carola Mittag</em><br>Having recently watched the 1987 psychological thriller <em>Fatal Attraction</em>, I started wondering about attractions that can actually become distractions; aren’t they really flip sides of the same coin? Examples of attractions/distractions may include alcohol, drugs, gambling, social media, gaming and adrenaline highs (the need to put oneself in dangerous situations). These attractions/distractions may actually be a form of addiction that affect what and how we accomplish things in our personal and professional work lives. Attractions/distractions offer an alternative reality which allows us to escape from those things that require focus, effort, application, commitment, concentration and work.</p>



<p>How distraction manifests itself in the workplace can impact the safety of not only the affected worker but also coworkers. Smartphones, the internet, social media and email are among the 10 biggest workplace distractors. Distractions can pose serious risks to the safety and well-being of employees, and it is crucial to address them effectively.</p>



<p>Fatal distractions in the workplace refer to any activity or object that diverts an employee&#8217;s attention away from their tasks and responsibilities, potentially leading to accidents, injuries, or even fatalities. These distractions can come in various forms, such as excessive noise, frequent interruptions, personal electronic devices, or inadequate ergonomic setups.</p>



<p>To eliminate or manage fatal distractions, it is essential to create a culture of awareness and accountability. This starts with comprehensive training programs that educate employees about the potential dangers of distractions and the importance of staying focused on the job. By promoting a safe and distraction-free work environment, the likelihood of accidents and injuries can be reduced.</p>



<p>Implementing effective policies and procedures is a critical step in managing fatal distractions. This can include establishing clear guidelines for the use of personal electronic devices, managing noise levels in the workplace and creating designated quiet areas for focused work. Additionally, providing employees with ergonomic equipment and workstations can help minimize physical distractions to promote productivity.</p>



<p>Regular communication and feedback with employees are key to identifying and addressing potential distractions. Encouraging open dialogue allows employees to express their concerns and suggest improvements. It is important to encourage employees to report any distractions they observe and provide the necessary support to address these issues promptly.</p>



<p>A commitment to eliminating and managing fatal distractions in the workplace emphasizes the importance of creating a safe and focused work environment. By implementing comprehensive training programs, establishing effective policies, and fostering open communication, distractions can be minimized to ensure the well-being of employees.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg" alt="carola-picture" class="wp-image-7832" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-416x624.jpg 416w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-scaled.jpg 1707w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>


<p>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Watch for next month’s Blog published in the second week of September</p>



<p>Sincerely,</p>



<p>Carola Mittag</p>



<p>Consultant and Editor for Mentor Safety Consultants Inc.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/fatal-distraction/">FATAL DISTRACTION</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALZHEIMERS IN THE WORKPLACE</title>
		<link>https://mentorsafety.com/alzheimers-in-the-workplace/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Wright]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2023 12:59:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Mentor Safety Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[accommodation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[disease]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusive]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mentorsafety.com/clear-the-aircraft-copy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>-Carola MittagMy friend Mark is older than me by two months to the day. I always teased him that he was much older. Mark is not only a friend but [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/alzheimers-in-the-workplace/">ALZHEIMERS IN THE WORKPLACE</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>-Carola Mittag</em><br>My friend Mark is older than me by two months to the day. I always teased him that he was much older. Mark is not only a friend but is a certified health and safety trainer who taught for me when I had my own safety company. He was well-liked by the participants because he had a wonderful sense of humour that made a day of learning material that was not always very interesting, easy. Mark had a natural ability to read his participants and speak to them at their level of understanding while ensuring that at the end of the day they knew their “stuff’ and left the training feeling good about themselves because he had helped them understand what they had come to learn.</p>



<p>When I sold my company to Mentor Safety, Mark and I lost touch; this saddened me, and I approached several mutual acquaintances until I finally “found” Mark after nearly two years. He was residing in a long-term care residence for people afflicted by dementia and Alzheimer’s. When I went to visit him in the LTC he did not recognize me. Obviously, Alzheimer’s had taken hold and progressed very aggressively.</p>



<p>I began to think about the onset of dementia or Alzheimer’s in workers who may be performing hazardous work or working in hazardous work environments. An affected worker may not be aware of their condition or worse, may be aware but unwilling to admit that their abilities are declining and thereby endangering themselves and others.</p>



<p>It is essential for employers to have a clear understanding of how to handle situations where an employee is suspected of having dementia or Alzheimer&#8217;s disease. These conditions can significantly impact an individual&#8217;s ability to perform their job effectively and safely and may require additional support and accommodation. Here are some important guidelines for employers to consider in such circumstances:</p>



<p><strong>1. Educate yourself:</strong> Familiarize yourself with the signs and symptoms of dementia and Alzheimer&#8217;s disease. This will help you recognize potential red flags and take appropriate action.</p>



<p><strong>2. Observe and document:</strong> If you suspect an employee may be experiencing cognitive decline, carefully observe their behavior and job performance. Document specific incidents or concerns, including any changes in memory, attention, or problem-solving abilities.</p>



<p><strong>3. Maintain confidentiality:</strong> It is crucial to handle this matter with utmost sensitivity and maintain the employee&#8217;s confidentiality. Only share information with those who need to know, such as HR personnel or supervisors directly involved in supporting the employee.</p>



<p><strong>4. Communicate openly:</strong> Initiate a conversation with the employee in private and with compassion. Express concern for their well-being and discuss any observed changes in their job performance. Encourage them to seek medical advice and offer support in accessing appropriate resources.</p>



<p><strong>5. Accommodate reasonable requests:</strong> If the employee has received a diagnosis of dementia or Alzheimer&#8217;s disease, engage in an interactive process to identify reasonable accommodations that can help them continue to perform their job duties. This may include adjustments to their workload, flexible scheduling, or providing additional training and support.</p>



<p><strong>6. Seek legal guidance:</strong> Consult with legal professionals to ensure compliance with applicable laws and regulations regarding employee rights and accommodation. This will help you navigate any potential legal implications while supporting the employee effectively.</p>



<p>Handling situations involving dementia or Alzheimer&#8217;s disease requires empathy, understanding, and a commitment to maintaining the dignity and well-being of the employee. By following these guidelines, employers can create a supportive and inclusive work environment for all employees, including those facing cognitive challenges. In all situations, everyone in the workplace has the right to remain safe and return home to their families at the end of the day.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg" alt="carola-picture" class="wp-image-7832" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-416x624.jpg 416w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-scaled.jpg 1707w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>


<p>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Watch for next month’s Blog published in the second week of August</p>



<p>Sincerely,</p>



<p>Carola Mittag</p>



<p>Consultant and Editor for Mentor Safety Consultants Inc.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/alzheimers-in-the-workplace/">ALZHEIMERS IN THE WORKPLACE</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CLEAR THE AIRCRAFT!</title>
		<link>https://mentorsafety.com/clear-the-aircraft/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Wright]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 16:18:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Mentor Safety Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Accident Investigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[competent person]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inspection]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IRS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[OHSA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[supervisor]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mentorsafety.com/twenty-five-cent-driver-copy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>-Carola MittagThis coming weekend I will say a final goodbye and deliver a eulogy for a high school friend who passed away as the result of a cerebral hemorrhage. To [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/clear-the-aircraft/">CLEAR THE AIRCRAFT!</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>-Carola Mittag</em><br>This coming weekend I will say a final goodbye and deliver a eulogy for a high school friend who passed away as the result of a cerebral hemorrhage. To have known Barry was to have known one of the most kind, compassionate and detailed people one could ever meet. He was a commercial pilot with a passion for flying from a very young age who came from a family of pilots. Flying was in his blood.</p>



<p>Barry had a wonderful sense of humour. What I remember him most for is his meticulous attention to detail and protocol as exhibited in this excerpt from the tribute I will pay him.</p>



<p><em>… he was a man of precision, care and exactness. Imagine this scene: in the middle of a grass field, with <strong>not a single person or other aircraft in sight</strong> on the ground or in the air, Barry, having completed the exterior aircraft check and pre-flight checklist, is now sitting in the pilot’s seat with me beside him when he opens the window and calls out in his loudest voice “clear the aircraft”. I suppose to the pilots in the room this may not seem funny, but to a non-aviation individual, this was comical. CLEAR THE AIRCRAFT!</em></p>



<p>Barry was the type of pilot who could have landed the airplane on the Hudson River (Miracle on the Hudson &#8211; gliding the plane to&nbsp;ditch&nbsp;in the&nbsp;Hudson River off Midtown Manhattan in 2009). Barry was the type of pilot I would have entrusted my life to.</p>



<p>This is the kind of trust and confidence that workers should expect from their employers and supervisors. They are the ‘pilots’ of a business with the responsibility to guide their workers to a ‘safe landing’. This responsibility must never simply be given to an individual because of seniority; this responsibility is a learned position that brings with it accountability, obligation, knowledge and duty. The <em>Occupational Health and Safety Act </em>has specific requirements and defines a supervisor as “a person who has charge of a workplace or authority over a worker”. With the high expectations and legal responsibilities that come with the supervisory position, supervisors must be equipped to carry out their roles to meet Ministry of labour guidelines competently. <strong><em>OHSA S. 27 (1)(2)</em></strong></p>



<p>One of the first things a Ministry inspector will ask for when conducting a surprise inspection is documentation that a Supervisor has received training to competently carry out their duties. Do they understand the role of the Internal Responsibility System (IRS); do they know how to navigate the Green Book (OHSA and regulations); do they adhere to and enforce the company’s health and safety policies and procedures; do they know how to identify and manage hazards; are they able to conduct an accident investigation and, very importantly, do they have the skills to communicate with employees to keep them safe?</p>



<p>Becoming a competent supervisor does not just happen, it is a learned skill and position that carries with it legal responsibilities that, if not met, can lead to fines from the Ministry, especially in the case of an incident or accident where training cannot be proven with proper training records.</p>



<p>May all workers have a Barry in their lives whom they can trust to keep them safe from harm in the workplace.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg" alt="carola-picture" class="wp-image-7832" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-416x624.jpg 416w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-scaled.jpg 1707w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>


<p>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Watch for next month’s Blog published in the second week of July</p>



<p>Sincerely,</p>



<p>Carola Mittag</p>



<p>Consultant and Editor for Mentor Safety Consultants Inc.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/clear-the-aircraft/">CLEAR THE AIRCRAFT!</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE TWENTY-FIVE CENT DRIVER</title>
		<link>https://mentorsafety.com/twenty-five-cent-driver/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Wright]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2023 17:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Mentor Safety Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Accident Investigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[audit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inspection]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[JHSC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Safety Management System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[safety procedure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[supervisor]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mentorsafety.com/marketplace-fanatic-copy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>-Carola MittagWhen I was a child and pennies were still in circulation, it was always interesting to see who would bend over to pick up the penny that was laying [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/twenty-five-cent-driver/">THE TWENTY-FIVE CENT DRIVER</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>-Carola Mittag</em><br>When I was a child and pennies were still in circulation, it was always interesting to see who would bend over to pick up the penny that was laying on the sidewalk on our way to or from school. The younger the child, the more likely it was that they would pick up that cent. As we got older it became uncool to bother stooping for that penny (although I always did secretly). And as we progressed from elementary school to junior high and then secondary school, bending down to pick up even a nickel or dime became less likely. Not only was it uncool, but it also gave the bullies reason to make snide remarks or tease the person who “lowered” themselves to pick up that coin.</p>



<p>Having gone to university, held a professional job for many years and am now happily retired, I still have to do my regular grocery shopping. I shop at a grocery store that has its buggies chained together. To release one of these shopping carts it is necessary to insert a quarter into a slot on the buggy; then, when your shopping is done, you can retrieve your quarter by retuning the buggy to the chained carts. I find it amazing that, no matter the weather, rain, sleet, hail or snow, people conscientiously return their cart to get back their twenty-five cents. Very, very rarely will you see an abandoned cart in the grocery store’s parking lot.</p>



<p>Today, even though a quarter has little buying power, people go to great lengths to get back their coin. I wonder if they ever think back to the times that they just walked by a penny, nickel or dime.</p>



<p>What has all this got to do with health and safety? I thought about a saying that is as old as the hills “<em>The devil is in the details.</em>” Those who return their carts to retrieve their quarters are paying attention to a little, seemingly, inconsequential detail; after all it’s only twenty-five cents.</p>



<p>“It will only take a second”; I’ve always done it this way”; Only this once”; It won’t happen to me”; What can go wrong?”; “But they did it like that”; “It’s only …….”.</p>



<p>How many times have we heard someone say any of these things or thought and said them ourselves? Whether it is workers following written safety procedures, or supervisors conducting site inspections, or JHSC members conducting an accident investigation, <em>the devil is in the details</em>! It sounds like an ominous warning, doesn’t it? But in fact, it is an expression used to point out that&nbsp;one should pay attention to all they do. Even the grandest project depends on the success of the smallest components. It may be the tiniest detail that, if not paid close attention to, could possibly ruin all your efforts not to mention cause injury, illness or even death. It is important to identify the details to avoid tragic consequences.</p>



<p>Safety audits are used to identify weaknesses in safety programs and processes in order to identify corrective actions that must be taken. Safety audits also identify whether or not a company is in compliance with the appropriate&nbsp;safety regulations. MENTOR’s safety audit is a structured process that is used to collect information relating to your company’s efficiency, effectiveness, and reliability. This type of inspection is more thorough than technical inspections or spot-check inspections, as it also involves reviewing your company’s safety documentation in order to determine how the company can improve its total health and&nbsp;safety management system.</p>



<p>People choose their actions, some in great detail and some lackadaisically. The consequences of those choices can mean the difference between a happy healthy future or one with lasting negative implications. Paying attention to details is never time wasted!</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg" alt="carola-picture" class="wp-image-7832" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-416x624.jpg 416w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-scaled.jpg 1707w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>


<p>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Watch for next month’s Blog published in the second week of June.</p>



<p>Sincerely,</p>



<p>Carola Mittag</p>



<p>Consultant and Editor for Mentor Safety Consultants Inc.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/twenty-five-cent-driver/">THE TWENTY-FIVE CENT DRIVER</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MARKETPLACE FANATIC</title>
		<link>https://mentorsafety.com/marketplace-fanatic/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Wright]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 13:44:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Mentor Safety Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CCOHS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[working alone]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mentorsafety.com/proud-mama-copy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>-Carola MittagI’m a self-professed Marketplace Fanatic. Usually children take on some of their parents’ habits, but I have become a Marketplace enthusiast after my sons both showed me the things [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/marketplace-fanatic/">MARKETPLACE FANATIC</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>-Carola Mittag</em><br>I’m a self-professed Marketplace Fanatic. Usually children take on some of their parents’ habits, but I have become a Marketplace enthusiast after my sons both showed me the things that they scored at almost unbelievable prices. I have always been a believer in reduce, reuse, recycle. This new fixation has taken that belief to a whole new level.&nbsp;</p>



<p>It is not that I need anything; as a matter of fact I should be getting rid of things at this point in my life. However, there is a compulsion to search for that. one. item. that perhaps, I just cannot do without. And I have found some totally frivolous items that are beautifying my home now and were once prized by their original owners. By the same token, I am posting things on Marketplace that are no longer needed, loved or wanted. Having taken over my parents’ house a few years back, I had to give away and sell many items that were not relevant to my lifestyle and design choices.</p>



<p>The process for purchasing an item from Marketplace is to send an offer, or deposit, or full payment to hold the item for the buyer to pick up at an arranged time. The pick-up could be from the seller’s home or at an agreed upon public place. The process for selling an item is to list it on Marketplace, describe the item and post the asking price. When posting an item the seller is asked whether their item will be available for viewing and pick-up at their location or at a pre-arranged location.</p>



<p>This got me to thinking about safety risks. There is the risk to the vendor who lists something for a potential buyer to come and view. In a well-known case in 2013, Tim Bosma listed a pickup truck for sale. An assumed potential buyer came to take it for a test drive with Mr. Bosma. A Hamilton Spectator headline <em>Tim Bosma goes out for a test rive never to return home</em> tells of the tragic outcome that Mr. Bosma was killed by the assumed buyer.</p>



<p>Until now I have had people come to my home when I’ve had something to sell <strong>and</strong> let them in if it was a larger item they were interested in. I live alone. I have put my safety at risk.</p>



<p>The key here is the word “alone” or “lone”. Lone workers may be at&nbsp;increased risk of confrontations or even violence, particularly if they are on shift during late night hours. Lone workers must be able to get assistance if they are injured or there is an emergency.<strong> </strong>What can be done to help a lone worker stay safe? Here are some things to help ensure the safety of a lone worker:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Assess the hazards of your workplace.</li>



<li>Avoid having a lone worker whenever possible, especially for jobs with a recognized risk.</li>



<li>Provide appropriate training and education to lone workers and those tasked to respond when there is concern.</li>



<li>Schedule higher risk jobs to be carried out during regular working hours or when another worker is available to help in an emergency.</li>



<li>Establish a check-in procedure. Make sure that regular contact is kept with all workers.</li>



<li>Establish ways to account for people (visually or verbally) while they are working.</li>
</ul>



<p>For more information on working alone visit the CCOHS information page. <a href="https://www.ccohs.ca/oshanswers/hsprograms/alone/workingalone.html#:~:text=With%20hazardous%20products.,is%20a%20potential%20for%20violence.">CLICK HERE</a></p>



<p>While it isn’t always hazardous to work alone, it can be when other circumstances are present. Whether a situation is a high or low risk will depend on the location, type of work, interaction with the public, or the consequences of an emergency, incident, injury, etc. The wide variety of possible circumstances makes it important to assess each situation individually.</p>



<p>I’ve come to realize that almost all events in my life must be viewed with an eye to safety; whether, as a marketplace fanatic or as an employee at risk when working alone.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg" alt="carola-picture" class="wp-image-7832" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-416x624.jpg 416w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-scaled.jpg 1707w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>


<p>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Watch for next month’s Blog published in the first week of May.</p>



<p>Sincerely,</p>



<p>Carola Mittag</p>



<p>Consultant and Editor for Mentor Safety Consultants Inc.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/marketplace-fanatic/">MARKETPLACE FANATIC</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>4 Year Consumer Choice Award Winners</title>
		<link>https://mentorsafety.com/4-year-consumer-choice-award-winners/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Wright]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 13:23:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Mentor Safety Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[certification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[confined space]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[elevated work platform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forklift]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ministry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[working at heights]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mentorsafety.com/proud-mama-copy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>-Consumer Choice AwardsConsumer Choice Award has chosen Mentor Safety Consultants as the winner in the Workplace Safety Training category for London, Ontario. This is the fourth time that the company [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/4-year-consumer-choice-award-winners/">4 Year Consumer Choice Award Winners</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><a href="https://www.ccaward.com/award-winners/london-greater-region/best-health-safety-training/mentor-safety-consultants/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-15762" width="418" height="278" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-300x200.jpg 300w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-768x512.jpg 768w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-416x277.jpg 416w" sizes="(max-width: 418px) 100vw, 418px" /></a></figure></div>


<p><em>-Consumer Choice Award</em>s<br>Consumer Choice Award has chosen Mentor Safety Consultants as the winner in the Workplace Safety Training category for London, Ontario. This is the fourth time that the company has won the coveted award. Using independently procured data, Consumer Choice Award recognizes and promotes business excellence. As the only winners in the category, each Award winner is the undisputed customer favorite in their region.</p>



<p>Mentor Safety Consultants was founded by Jamie Wright, CRSP, CMSE, CHSC. As the Director and Senior Consultant, Jamie has successfully built a company based on his passion for safety in the workplace and his 30+ years of experience in the safety world. The company today implements safety solutions that are functional and in sync with the demands of its clients.</p>



<p>The team at Mentor provides industry-specific hands-on training. This domain-focused expertise is customized to the real-world needs of the company’s clients. More than mere safety protocols, the objective of the company is to foster a culture of safety in the organizations they work with. It is recognized that Mentor Safety Consultants do this at an award-winning level and have cemented themselves as high-quality providers of workplace safety training.</p>



<p>The business has training programs including Chief Prevention Officer Approved Working at Heights and Joint Health and Safety Committee Certification, as well as Forklift Operator, Elevated Work Platform Operator, Confined Space Entry, and many more. Mentor Safety Consultants can deliver training at their clients’ sites or, they can host the training at their 2,200 sq. ft. training facility in London which features many visual and hands-on learning aids. Learners can get practical experience with vertical and horizontal lifelines, different fall protection systems, operations of a forklift and elevated work platform as well as other industry-leading safety equipment.</p>



<p>The business doesn’t just deliver safety training. Mentor Safety Consultants specializes in providing practical, on-site safety support. They don’t just develop safety programs, and expect the clients to take care of their implementation. They’re with their clients and their employees throughout the process to make sure that all aspects of safety are implemented and ingrained in the system.</p>



<p>The company’s consulting services include on-site workplace inspections and audits, assistance with the Ministry of Labour, Immigration Training and Skills Development (MLITSD) Audits, hazard and risk assessments, machine guarding, lock-out programs, technical interpretation of safety standards, safety policy and culture development, conflict resolution, workplace violence, and harassment management, and 24/7 technical safety support.</p>



<p>For Mentor Safety Consultants, the goal has always been to create, nurture, and sustain safer working conditions. As the Consumer Choice Award shows, that’s a mission its clients have come to believe in.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://www.ccaward.com/award-winners/london-greater-region/best-health-safety-training/mentor-safety-consultants/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/consumer-choice-award-2023.png" alt="award ribbon for 2023 " class="wp-image-15197" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/consumer-choice-award-2023.png 150w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/consumer-choice-award-2023-100x100.png 100w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/consumer-choice-award-2023-24x24.png 24w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/consumer-choice-award-2023-48x48.png 48w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/consumer-choice-award-2023-96x96.png 96w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px" /></a></figure></div><p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/4-year-consumer-choice-award-winners/">4 Year Consumer Choice Award Winners</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>PROUD MAMA</title>
		<link>https://mentorsafety.com/proud-mama/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Wright]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 13:49:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Mentor Safety Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[emergency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PEMEP]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mentorsafety.com/a-case-of-workplace-violence-ignored-copy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>-Carola MittagNo matter how old your child, when they receive accolades for having done something well, it is alright to be a proud mama. My 46 year old son works [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/proud-mama/">PROUD MAMA</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>-Carola Mittag</em><br>No matter how old your child, when they receive accolades for having done something well, it is alright to be a proud mama.</p>



<p>My 46 year old son works for one of the largest employers in Niagara Region. His official title is Property Maintenance Lead. In this position he has responsibility for hiring people to work alongside him in various and diverse jobs. Very little is repetitive; oftentimes decisions must be made on-the-fly, as when an emergency situation arises at any of the properties for which he is responsible.</p>



<p>Recently, for the first time in three years (because of the pandemic), his employer held a two-day safety conference at which educational safety seminars and sessions were offered and at which employees were recognized for their part in in maintaining a safe work environment. On the crystal award that my son received is this inscription: <em>Awarded to an individual who shows dedication, commitment and lives by the values of our Superior Safety Culture.</em></p>



<p>There is so much to say about recognition.</p>



<ol class="wp-block-list" type="1">
<li>The employer is to be commended for promoting health and safety and acknowledging the health and safety performance of its employees.</li>



<li>An employee who receives this kind of recognition will, without doubt, continue to work in a fashion that keeps his/her own safety topmost in mind in all work tasks.</li>



<li>An employee who receives this kind of recognition will also ensure and encourage coworkers to always work safely.</li>



<li>An employer’s recognition is its statement of commitment to continually monitor the state of health and safety of its <strong>P</strong>eople, its <strong>E</strong>quipment, the <strong>M</strong>aterials, the <strong>E</strong>nvironment and the <strong>P</strong>rocesses (PEMEP). Each of these factors must be considered when recognizing, assessing, and controlling hazards. When an employer does this, the workplace will be healthy and efficient.</li>
</ol>



<p>Understandably, my son and I have had many conversations around health and safety. On several occasions he has given me examples of where written health and safety policies collide with practicality and even common sense. When I had my own health and safety company this was probably the most often voiced complaint by workers. I always tried to explain that laws, regulations and rules are written in response to things that have happened and cannot be applied to unprecedented situations that have not yet occurred. However, I found this quote by Thomas Jefferson, the 3rd U.S. President which I believe makes sense and may help explain why and how law is created: <em>Common sense is the foundation of all authorities, of the laws themselves, and of their construction.</em></p>



<p>Common sense can help formulate laws, but laws cannot help someone have common sense. It is for those, who lack common sense, that the laws are written.</p>



<p>My son is wise, has common sense and understands the underlying reasons for the law. I trust, that when he must make an on-the-fly decision, he will base that decision on situational common sense and law.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg" alt="carola-picture" class="wp-image-7832" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-416x624.jpg 416w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-scaled.jpg 1707w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>


<p>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Watch for next month’s Blog published in the first week of April.</p>



<p>Sincerely,</p>



<p>Carola Mittag</p>



<p>Consultant and Editor for Mentor Safety Consultants Inc.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/proud-mama/">PROUD MAMA</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A CASE OF WORKPLACE VIOLENCE &#8211; IGNORED</title>
		<link>https://mentorsafety.com/a-case-of-workplace-violence-ignored/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Wright]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 16:08:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Mentor Safety Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[employer responsibility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[harassment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[investigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[OHSA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[workplace accident]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mentorsafety.com/guilty-until-proven-innocent-copy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>-Carola MittagAs I sat down at my computer today to begin February’s Blog, I was interrupted by a phone call from an acquaintance who had moved from Ontario to New [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/a-case-of-workplace-violence-ignored/">A CASE OF WORKPLACE VIOLENCE &#8211; IGNORED</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>-Carola Mittag</em><br>As I sat down at my computer today to begin February’s Blog, I was interrupted by a phone call from an acquaintance who had moved from Ontario to New York City about two years ago. After the initial “how are yous” and catching up, he began to tell me about his recent experience in the workplace.</p>



<p>As background, we met many years ago and have remained in touch periodically over the years. My friend is an international keynote speaker and has spent the last 20 years transforming people, workplaces and communities through empathic behavior change. The emphasis on his presentations focuses on empowering people to be the best versions of themselves.</p>



<p>This friend is an avid advocate for living healthy through eating well and keeping physically fit. He started working for an employer last year and was involved in organizing volunteers for various events hosted by that organization. A few weeks ago he was physically assaulted (punched) by another employee. Besides being totally caught off guard, this goes against everything he believes in and discusses in his presentations, that being “to help staff become more self-aware of their interactions and behaviors and to increase employee engagement”.</p>



<p>The assault was reported to the NYC police where the response was that they wouldn’t do anything because he wasn’t injured and nothing prosecutable happened. The offender had taken my friend’s phone and tossed it away shortly after; he was able to retrieve it. The police said, had the phone been taken, then there would have been a felony committed and grounds for an arrest, but not for the physical assault.</p>



<p>We also talked about the follow-up by HR and management which, to put it simply, was almost non-existent.</p>



<p>This was a clear-cut case of workplace violence. How differently it would have been handled in Ontario. Under Bill 168; Occupational Health and Safety Amendment Act (Violence and Harassment in the Workplace), it&nbsp;is the employer’s responsibility to deal with this and ensure staff feel safe and work in a healthy environment. Violence and harassment investigations are mandatory when there is a formal complaint, or if the employer otherwise becomes aware of behaviour that contravenes the company’s policy.</p>



<p>Complaints should be investigated by someone in senior management, an HR representative and a member of the JHSC or health and safety representative. Investigation stages may include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Document review</li>



<li>Interviews with the complainant</li>



<li>Witness interviews</li>



<li>An interview or interviews with the alleged harasser</li>



<li>Examination of photos if applicable</li>



<li>A review of any relevant electronic records, such as emails, phone records, texts, or video</li>
</ul>



<p>All investigation actions (meetings, interviews, etc.), steps, and reviews must be carefully documented. Doing so supports due diligence. As well, the worker or workers who made the complaint must be kept apprised through the investigative process of the progress of the investigation.</p>



<p>I have also encountered workplace harassment, back in the day when it was overlooked, swept under the table and simply ignored. As we become more aware and open to discussing mental health, every incident of workplace violence and/or harassment must be addressed. It is an issue of a workplace’s health and safety culture.</p>



<p>I shifted from the original topic of this month’s Blog to tell this story as I felt it important to address the issue of workplace violence and how it is handled by HR and upper management.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg" alt="carola-picture" class="wp-image-7832" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-416x624.jpg 416w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-scaled.jpg 1707w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>


<p>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Watch for next month’s Blog published in the first week of March.</p>



<p>Sincerely,</p>



<p>Carola Mittag</p>



<p>Consultant and Editor for Mentor Safety Consultants Inc.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/a-case-of-workplace-violence-ignored/">A CASE OF WORKPLACE VIOLENCE &#8211; IGNORED</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
