<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>forklift Archives - Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</title>
	<atom:link href="https://mentorsafety.com/tag/forklift/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://mentorsafety.com/tag/forklift/</link>
	<description>Your Guide to Safety</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 15:11:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/cropped-mentor-safety-icon-only2-32x32.png</url>
	<title>forklift Archives - Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</title>
	<link>https://mentorsafety.com/tag/forklift/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>4 Year Consumer Choice Award Winners</title>
		<link>https://mentorsafety.com/4-year-consumer-choice-award-winners/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Wright]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 13:23:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Mentor Safety Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[certification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[confined space]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[elevated work platform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forklift]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ministry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[working at heights]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mentorsafety.com/proud-mama-copy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>-Consumer Choice AwardsConsumer Choice Award has chosen Mentor Safety Consultants as the winner in the Workplace Safety Training category for London, Ontario. This is the fourth time that the company [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/4-year-consumer-choice-award-winners/">4 Year Consumer Choice Award Winners</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><a href="https://www.ccaward.com/award-winners/london-greater-region/best-health-safety-training/mentor-safety-consultants/"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-15762" width="418" height="278" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-300x200.jpg 300w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-768x512.jpg 768w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/0035_CCA2023LONDON_HRM-reduced-416x277.jpg 416w" sizes="(max-width: 418px) 100vw, 418px" /></a></figure></div>


<p><em>-Consumer Choice Award</em>s<br>Consumer Choice Award has chosen Mentor Safety Consultants as the winner in the Workplace Safety Training category for London, Ontario. This is the fourth time that the company has won the coveted award. Using independently procured data, Consumer Choice Award recognizes and promotes business excellence. As the only winners in the category, each Award winner is the undisputed customer favorite in their region.</p>



<p>Mentor Safety Consultants was founded by Jamie Wright, CRSP, CMSE, CHSC. As the Director and Senior Consultant, Jamie has successfully built a company based on his passion for safety in the workplace and his 30+ years of experience in the safety world. The company today implements safety solutions that are functional and in sync with the demands of its clients.</p>



<p>The team at Mentor provides industry-specific hands-on training. This domain-focused expertise is customized to the real-world needs of the company’s clients. More than mere safety protocols, the objective of the company is to foster a culture of safety in the organizations they work with. It is recognized that Mentor Safety Consultants do this at an award-winning level and have cemented themselves as high-quality providers of workplace safety training.</p>



<p>The business has training programs including Chief Prevention Officer Approved Working at Heights and Joint Health and Safety Committee Certification, as well as Forklift Operator, Elevated Work Platform Operator, Confined Space Entry, and many more. Mentor Safety Consultants can deliver training at their clients’ sites or, they can host the training at their 2,200 sq. ft. training facility in London which features many visual and hands-on learning aids. Learners can get practical experience with vertical and horizontal lifelines, different fall protection systems, operations of a forklift and elevated work platform as well as other industry-leading safety equipment.</p>



<p>The business doesn’t just deliver safety training. Mentor Safety Consultants specializes in providing practical, on-site safety support. They don’t just develop safety programs, and expect the clients to take care of their implementation. They’re with their clients and their employees throughout the process to make sure that all aspects of safety are implemented and ingrained in the system.</p>



<p>The company’s consulting services include on-site workplace inspections and audits, assistance with the Ministry of Labour, Immigration Training and Skills Development (MLITSD) Audits, hazard and risk assessments, machine guarding, lock-out programs, technical interpretation of safety standards, safety policy and culture development, conflict resolution, workplace violence, and harassment management, and 24/7 technical safety support.</p>



<p>For Mentor Safety Consultants, the goal has always been to create, nurture, and sustain safer working conditions. As the Consumer Choice Award shows, that’s a mission its clients have come to believe in.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://www.ccaward.com/award-winners/london-greater-region/best-health-safety-training/mentor-safety-consultants/"><img decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/consumer-choice-award-2023.png" alt="award ribbon for 2023 " class="wp-image-15197" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/consumer-choice-award-2023.png 150w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/consumer-choice-award-2023-100x100.png 100w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/consumer-choice-award-2023-24x24.png 24w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/consumer-choice-award-2023-48x48.png 48w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/consumer-choice-award-2023-96x96.png 96w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px" /></a></figure></div><p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/4-year-consumer-choice-award-winners/">4 Year Consumer Choice Award Winners</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
