<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>policies Archives - Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</title>
	<atom:link href="https://mentorsafety.com/tag/policies/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://mentorsafety.com/tag/policies/</link>
	<description>Your Guide to Safety</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 13:32:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/cropped-mentor-safety-icon-only2-32x32.png</url>
	<title>policies Archives - Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</title>
	<link>https://mentorsafety.com/tag/policies/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>FATAL DISTRACTION</title>
		<link>https://mentorsafety.com/fatal-distraction/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Wright]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 13:28:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Mentor Safety Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[distractions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ergonomic equipment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[policies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[training programs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mentorsafety.com/alzheimers-in-the-workplace-copy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>-Carola MittagHaving recently watched the 1987 psychological thriller Fatal Attraction, I started wondering about attractions that can actually become distractions; aren’t they really flip sides of the same coin? Examples [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/fatal-distraction/">FATAL DISTRACTION</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>-Carola Mittag</em><br>Having recently watched the 1987 psychological thriller <em>Fatal Attraction</em>, I started wondering about attractions that can actually become distractions; aren’t they really flip sides of the same coin? Examples of attractions/distractions may include alcohol, drugs, gambling, social media, gaming and adrenaline highs (the need to put oneself in dangerous situations). These attractions/distractions may actually be a form of addiction that affect what and how we accomplish things in our personal and professional work lives. Attractions/distractions offer an alternative reality which allows us to escape from those things that require focus, effort, application, commitment, concentration and work.</p>



<p>How distraction manifests itself in the workplace can impact the safety of not only the affected worker but also coworkers. Smartphones, the internet, social media and email are among the 10 biggest workplace distractors. Distractions can pose serious risks to the safety and well-being of employees, and it is crucial to address them effectively.</p>



<p>Fatal distractions in the workplace refer to any activity or object that diverts an employee&#8217;s attention away from their tasks and responsibilities, potentially leading to accidents, injuries, or even fatalities. These distractions can come in various forms, such as excessive noise, frequent interruptions, personal electronic devices, or inadequate ergonomic setups.</p>



<p>To eliminate or manage fatal distractions, it is essential to create a culture of awareness and accountability. This starts with comprehensive training programs that educate employees about the potential dangers of distractions and the importance of staying focused on the job. By promoting a safe and distraction-free work environment, the likelihood of accidents and injuries can be reduced.</p>



<p>Implementing effective policies and procedures is a critical step in managing fatal distractions. This can include establishing clear guidelines for the use of personal electronic devices, managing noise levels in the workplace and creating designated quiet areas for focused work. Additionally, providing employees with ergonomic equipment and workstations can help minimize physical distractions to promote productivity.</p>



<p>Regular communication and feedback with employees are key to identifying and addressing potential distractions. Encouraging open dialogue allows employees to express their concerns and suggest improvements. It is important to encourage employees to report any distractions they observe and provide the necessary support to address these issues promptly.</p>



<p>A commitment to eliminating and managing fatal distractions in the workplace emphasizes the importance of creating a safe and focused work environment. By implementing comprehensive training programs, establishing effective policies, and fostering open communication, distractions can be minimized to ensure the well-being of employees.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg" alt="carola-picture" class="wp-image-7832" srcset="https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-416x624.jpg 416w, https://mentorsafety.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/carola-mittag-wsg-president-1-scaled.jpg 1707w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>


<p>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Watch for next month’s Blog published in the second week of September</p>



<p>Sincerely,</p>



<p>Carola Mittag</p>



<p>Consultant and Editor for Mentor Safety Consultants Inc.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://mentorsafety.com/fatal-distraction/">FATAL DISTRACTION</a> appeared first on <a href="https://mentorsafety.com">Mentor Safety Consultants - A Safety Co Partner</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
